<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A compendious answer to a book called A brief survay of the judgement of Mr. John Goodvvin, and the Church of God walking with him, touching their reasons of dissenting from many of their brethren, in these imprtant heads of doctrine; 1. Election and reprobation. 2. The death of Christ. 3. The grace of God in and about conversion. 4. The liberty or power of the will, or of the creature man. 5. The perseverance of the saints. VVherein the absurdities of all their dissenting doctrines are clearly exhibited, by a loving friend to the truth it self, Ellis Bradshaw.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, Ellis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4139A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212996</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825537</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825537</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29921</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29921)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1755:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A compendious answer to a book called A brief survay of the judgement of Mr. John Goodvvin, and the Church of God walking with him, touching their reasons of dissenting from many of their brethren, in these imprtant heads of doctrine; 1. Election and reprobation. 2. The death of Christ. 3. The grace of God in and about conversion. 4. The liberty or power of the will, or of the creature man. 5. The perseverance of the saints. VVherein the absurdities of all their dissenting doctrines are clearly exhibited, by a loving friend to the truth it self, Ellis Bradshaw.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, Ellis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by H. Hills, and are to be sold by T. Bradshaw at the signe of the Three Bibles at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LII. [1652]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregational churches --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29921:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29921:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>COMPENDIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S ANSWER</hi> To a Book called A BRIEF SURVAY Of the Judgement of <hi>Mr.</hi> JOHN GOODVVIN, and the Church of God walking with him, touching their Reaſons of diſſenting from many of their Brethren, in theſe Important Heads of Doctrine;
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Election and Reprobation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Death of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The grace of God in and about Converſion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>The liberty or power of the will, or of the creature man.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>The Perſeverance of the Saints.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> VVherein the Abſurdities of all their diſſenting Doctrines are clearly exhibited, By a Loving Friend to the Truth it ſelf, ELLIS BRADSHAW.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Joh. 5.13, 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Theſe things have I written unto you that believe on the name of the Son of God, that yee may know that yee have eternall life, and that yee may believe on the name of the Son of God.</p>
               <p>And we know that we are of God, and the whole world lyeth in wickedneſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Hills,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>T. Brewſter</hi> at the ſigne of the Three Bibles at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> M.DC.LII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29921:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29921:2"/>
            <head>To his Excellency <hi>OLIVER CROMWELL</hi> Lord Generall of the Forces of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ENGLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Excellency,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Otwithſtanding I am conſcious, in the ſight of God, of my own unſuitableſſe for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking ſuch a task as this, both for want of learning &amp; education anſwerable, and the meanneſſe alſo of my Reputation: Yet finding this book of M. <hi>John Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wins,</hi> and his whole Church, ſo long allready extant in print, as ſince the 30. of <hi>May,</hi> and no Anſwer to it; And finding it very dangerous in many points of doctrine, wherein they diſſent from many of their acknowledged brethren, and cauſing a ſeparation, as is notedly known: And having underſtanding, through the grace of God, of ſome peculiar notions, that rightly apprehended, give a full reſult to all the difference in hand, in all theſe five particulars diſſented in; I thought it my duty, in love to the ſoules of ſo many brethren, that not only
<pb facs="tcp:29921:3"/>walk in the fear of God, and profeſſion of Religion, in which they are reall Practitioners, as their judgement leads them; but have been reall Engagers, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, for the Parliament and Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> as is publiquely known: I am content to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as a fool in ſome mens eyes, in undertaking ſo great an encounter in ſuch deep Divinity, that hath troubled the wiſeſt and deepeſt judgements in all ages, and never as yet brought to a clear reſult, but is ſtill left doubtfull in all their writings, never obtaining an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible aſſent, but many ſtrange diſſentings have ever appeared in all ages about theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>However, I for my part, being ſatisfied, both from ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, and clear Rationality in thoſe reſpects; and hoping in God that he will make me able to clear it up, and make it obvious to any rationall apprehenſion, againſt any oppoſition that can be held forth by theſe diſſenting brethren; I have made thus bold, not only to oppoſe them, but have allſo preſumed to dedicate the ſame to your Noble Excellency, in regard they have led me in ſuch preſumption: That ſo your Excellency, if time permit, might judge of the truth, as you find it to appear; and not ſo much as ſeem to patronize or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance any groſſe errours, or abſurd tenents and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, farre unſuitable for eminent Chriſtians; A brief ſurvey whereof your Excellency may find after the Treatiſe; the which, if poſſible, I earneſtly deſire your Excellency would read, when time will permit from your important buſineſſe, if you cannot find time to read the other, that ſo you might ſee how farre it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a whole Church to erre, and that in Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls. Thus briefly, leſt I ſhould ſeem tedious, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you to the government of the Spirit of Truth, who dwelleth in you, and hath given you faith to go on ſtill,
<pb facs="tcp:29921:3"/>conquering and to conquer, and that on the Lambs ſide, togerher with them that are with him, the called, and choſen, and faithfull: And reſt, earneſtly deſiring, that you may ride on proſperouſly in the waies of Truth, and Meekneſſe, and Righteouſneſſe; Who is your Souldier and Servant allſo, in what you pleaſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ELLIS BRADSHAW.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29921:4"/>
            <head>To M. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> and the Church of God walking with him, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had not undertaken this encounter with you, if I had not been fortified with ſpeciall and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar notions and arguments, which you have not heard of from other men; and thoſe clearly deducible from ſacred Scripture. I am not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that ſome of your Brethren, from whom you diſſent, will approve ſome things that I have held forth; neither yet doe I approve all that they hold againſt your doctrine, as it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in divers Arguments, and Reaſons rendred. I ſhall deſire to hear from you either publickly, or in private, how you reſent ſuch notions, and how you apprehend them; that if any thing be dark or doubtfull therein, I might clear it up, what my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, and what the truth is allſo, as I doubt not but to do in a ſhort ſpace by the help of God. I hope your principles are ſuch, not to deſpiſe any rich treaſure, becauſe of the veſſell that hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it forth, but ſearch the Scriptures, whether theſe things be ſo. And beſides, I doe conceive that it much troubleth you, that you cannot conceive how to reconcile your Brethrens doctrines with the Attributes of God, and therefore are forced to diſſent and ſeparate from them much againſt your wils: All which, if it be true, it may poſſibly cauſe you ſo to deny your ſelves, as to ſubmit to the truth, when you ſee it, and give glory unto God, who is the Truth it ſelf, and the only Fountain from whence it cometh, through what ever pipes it is conveyed unto you. I
<pb facs="tcp:29921:4"/>much doubt not but you will acknowledge, that God hideth things from the wiſe and prudent, that he revealeth unto babes; and that on purpoſe that no fleſh ſhould glory in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, but that he that glorieth might glory in the Lord. And leſt men ſhould ſay, they have found out wiſedome; as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were too many for <hi>Gedeon,</hi> that the Lord ſhould deliver <hi>Iſrael</hi> into their hands, leſt they ſhould have ſaid, their own hands, and not the Lord, had ſaved them: So ſome men are too wiſe to have knowledge given them of ſome ſecrets, leſt the people ſhould idolize the men, as having found them out by their own wiſedome, &amp; not give glory unto God; but he will not give his glory to another: And therefore wiſe men ſometimes muſt be content to receive knowledge at the ſecond hand; and they are wiſe indeed, if they can be content to receive it from fools, yea from baſe things, in repute of the world, and mean, &amp; contemptible; and ſo they ſometimes muſt, or elſe be without. But I need not inform you of theſe things, ſave only to put you in remembrance: I therefore break off, and commit you to God, who is able to lead us into all truth, and to reveal unto us even his whole counſell, and work us up, through faith and love, to faithfull obedience, and ſubmiſſion to his will, and to make us perfect in every good word and work; Which the Lord grant both to you and me in his due time. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Brother and Friend in the Truth, <hi>ELLIS BRADSHAW.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:29921:5"/>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>thoſe who are Gods Elect cannot poſſibly periſh, whether they come to years of diſcretion ye or no, conſidering theſe ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? It is God that juſtifies, who ſhall condemn? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31, 32, 33, 34. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If it were poſſible they ſhould deceive even the very E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. Implying clearly that it is unpoſſible.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whom he did foreknow he alſo did predeſtinate to be conformed to the image of his ſonne, that he might be the firſt born of many brethren. Moreover, whom he did predeſtinate them he alſo called, and whom he called, them he alſo juſtified, and whom he juſtified, them he alſo glorified.</p>
            <p>Now give me leave I beſeech you in love to intreat you but to conſider the difference betwixt the Apoſtles ends, perſwaſion and judgement, and this your judgement which you propoſe to us; You confidently affirm you hold and teach, That God hath not decreed from eternity, to elect any perſon of mankind upon any terms, but that in caſe he liveth to years of diſcretion he may very poſſibly periſh notwithſtanding any ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> 1. In which expreſſion I firſt obſerve that your end is contradictious to the Apoſtles drift.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> For whereas the Apoſtles expreſſions tend for incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of all that have made their election ſure and are aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of it, to be exceeding confident that nothing can ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them from the love of Chriſt verſe 35.39. and that ſeeing God is for them, none can be againſt them, bringing in a ſtrong argument to back his aſſertion, to wit, He that ſpared not his own ſon, but delivered him up for us all, obſerve this [for us all] implies and includes all Gods Elect, as the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verſe clears.</p>
            <p>Now the Apoſtles argument lyeth thus, to wit, If God ſpared not his only ſon, but delivered him up for us all, that are Gods elect, verſe 32. How ſhall he not with him alſo freely give us all things. Implying an impoſſibility but that he ſhould with him give us all things needfull both for our ſouls and bodies; and make all things work together for our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29921:5"/>good, as verſe 28. ſo that God himſelf being for us nothing can be againſt us, verſe 31.</p>
            <p>So that the very reading of the text will ſatisfy any rational apprehenſion, that the drift of the Apoſtle is to build them up to a ſtrong confidence; that ſo they might have ſtrong conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and full aſſurance of faith, and without wavering, as <hi>He.</hi> 10.22, 23, and c. 6.18.</p>
            <p>Whereas the very end of your aſſertion tendeth to no other but to put if poſſible even Gods very Elect, and ſuch who know they are ſo, into doubts and fears: who ought not to caſt away their ſtrong confidence which hath great recompence of Reward, ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.35. for in ſo doing they caſt away even their ſpiritual life: <hi>For the just live by faith,</hi> as verſe 38.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. Secondly, I obſerve your judgement is contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious to the Apoſtles judgement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> For the Apoſtle was perſwaded that neither height, nor depth, nor any other Creature ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39. Us, I ſay, if we be his Elect. And the Apoſtle was perſwaded that if God be for us, none can be againſt us, nor pluck us out of his hands, nor lay anything to our charge, but we ſhall be more than conquerors, through him that loved us, as verſe 31, 32, 33, 37. And that without all peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whom God hath foreknown he alſo hath predeſtinate to be conformed to the image of his ſonne, And whom he hath predeſtinate them he alſo calleth; and whom he calleth, them he alſo juſtifieth, and whom he juſtifieth, them he alſo glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as v. 28, 29, 30.</p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle is of opinion and doth affirm <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17.18. That God willing more abundantly to ſhew unto the heirs of promiſe the immutabilitie of his counſel, confirmed it by an oath, that ſo they might have ſtrong conſolation.</p>
            <p>But you hold and teach that notwithſtanding any ſuch decree, or immutable counſel, or foreknowledge, or predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or election of God, yet if they come to years of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they may poſſibly periſh: which to me ſeemeth very ſtrange.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:29921:6"/>
            <p>Now you put in an ingredient ſo quite contradictory to what you aſſented to before, that I hope your own aſſentings when you ſee them unveiled, will clearly convince you that your own diſſentings are not only contradictious to your own aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, but to the truth it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> For you hold and teach that God hath not decreed from eternity to elect any perſon of mankind (upon any terms) but that in caſe he liveth to years of diſcretion he may very poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly periſh.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Wherein firſt you affirm as much as if you ſhould ſay, That God had not decreed from eternity to elect Chriſt himſelf upon any terms, but in caſe he lived, as that he did, to years of diſcretion, he might poſſibly have periſhed. The which I hope you will not affirm. And therefore thus far I hope you will grant conviction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, In that your generall terms do exclude all and every perſon of mankind as that in your apprehenſions not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the decree of God to have ſome elect (and that a certain number, as that you acknowledge, and that he hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changably decreed what that number ſhall be)</p>
            <p>Yet you affirm, as much as if you ſhould ſay, that all Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect may very poſſibly periſh, notwithſtanding Gods decree to ſave ſome. Thus far I hope alſo you will deny even you own aſſertions.</p>
            <p>Now in regard I hope you will grant that the Election of Chriſt ſtandeth ſure, and that he could not poſſibly periſh.</p>
            <p>I ſhall aſſume a little further that you will alſo grant that ſuch who are elected in time, by the ſame hand (that elected Chriſt in the fulneſs of time from the loines of the Virgin) ſuch I ſay whom God electeth, from the very loines of their natural parents, by means of propagation, as he did Chriſt: you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not for ſhame deny but their Election alſo ſtandeth ſure, ſo that they cannot poſſibly periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ar.</hi> But Chriſt which ſanctifieth, and they which are ſanctified, are all (of one) that is the are all (of God) as Chriſt himſelf was of God, for which cauſe he was not aſhamed to call them brethren, for it behoved Chriſt in all things to be made like unto his brethren, &amp;c. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11.17.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:29921:6"/>
            <p>They are not of the world as he was not of the world. <hi>John</hi> 17.14.16.</p>
            <p>If they were of the world, the world would love his own, but Chriſt hath choſen them out of the world, and therfore the world hateth them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.19.</p>
            <p>Ye have not choſen me, but I have choſen you, and ordained you, &amp;c. verſe 16. ſaith our bleſſed Savior, to whom God hath given power over all fleſh that he ſhould give eternal life to as many as God had given him. <hi>John</hi> 17.2.</p>
            <p>Some are of the world, and therefore it is that they ſpeak of the world, and the world heareth them.</p>
            <p>But ſome are of God, and he that knoweth God heareth them, but he that is not of God heareth them not; and thereby may be known the ſpirit of truth and the ſpirit of error: ſee 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.5, 6. And again, He that is of God heareth Gods words, ſaith Chriſt, ye therfore hear them not becauſe ye are not of God, <hi>John</hi> 8.47.</p>
            <p>So that it is clear ſome are of God before they hear God words, and do therfore hear them becauſe they are of God, and not of the world: For the truth is they are ſo of God by generation, as that God is the chief cauſe of their very ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or propagation from the very loines of their natural parents. And this is properly their actual election, which is accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in time according to his eternal purpoſe, or counſel of his will to elect in Chriſt; having in his immutable counſel, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined with himſelf, what he would effect and bring to paſs in time; for he worketh all things (in time) according to his eternal purpoſe or counſel of his will before there was time.</p>
            <p>But without all queſtion ſuch who are thus ſeparated by the hand of God through means of generation, and ſo are properly ſelected out of the world, as peculiarly his own; theſe you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but muſt needs acknowledge their election is ſure in the ſight of God, ſo as they cannot poſſibly periſh.</p>
            <p>And again, ſo many as God had called, juſtified, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, them you muſt needs acknowledge ſhall be glorified, and ſo cannot poſſibly periſh: elſe you deny theſe plain expreſſions of the Holy Ghoſt before cited, and go about alſo, as hath been ſaid, to put even the beſt and holieſt men into doubts, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29921:7"/>fears, whereas you ſhould labour to edifie in the faith and not to deſtroy their faith.</p>
            <p>So that I cannot imagine what you ſhould poſſibly mean, or intend in this doctrine; unleſs you ſo judge as that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God or counſel of his will before the world began, was not ſo capacious and comprehenſious as to determine before hand what ſhould certainly become of every particular perſon that ſhould be begotten from the beginning to the end: But only determined with himſelf concerning the ſpecies or certain kinds of men, in the groſs, or general and no further at all, as ſo you ſeem to expreſs your ſelf, ſaying,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is no Election, or Decree of Election of particular perſons as ſuch, but only of an intire species of men from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> In which aſſertion you plainly deny the omniſciency of God, and render him to us altogether blind in reſpect of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars till they be exiſtent, and ſo you alſo exclude the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt himſelf as hath been ſaid, and every other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of the Elect of God, out of his eternal purpoſe: as though he had not known as well the particulars, as the groſs and generall of all his works, from the beginning to the end.</p>
            <p>Whereas the text is clear, that he worketh all things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the counſel of his own will, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11. And it is alſo clear that his underſtanding is Infinite, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.5.</p>
            <p>So that he cannot poſſibly be ignorant any more of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars than of the intire ſpecies, or ſorts of people: for if he were ignorant of any thing; his underſtanding were not infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.</p>
            <p>And if he did any thing at all in time, that he had not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in himſelf in the counſel of his will before-time. Then he could not be ſaid to work all things according to his own purpoſe, or the counſel of his will.</p>
            <p>For if any particular work ſhould be effected by him which he did not purpoſe in the Counſel of his will; that particular work could not properly be ſaid to be effected according to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of his will, nor as he had purpoſed in himſelf, if he did not purpoſe that very particular work.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:29921:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But you it may be will object, <hi>That what is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to be done to or concerning all ſuch of the ſame kind or ſpecies, is alſo decreed to be done to every particular of ſuch species or kinds of poople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, true; But upon what ground can you poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly exclude out of the preſcience or foreknowledge of God, the foreſight and knowledge of every particular work that he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſheth in time? How can you prove that he did not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that very particular work?</p>
            <p>Can you poſſibly imagine that he did not foreſee from the very beginning all, paſt, preſent, and future occurrences, that have been, are, or ſhall be effected to the very end? How dare you limit the Holy One of Iſrael and ſo diminiſh his Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes? Whereas you well know His underſtanding is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Therefore he is not ignorant of any occurrences from the beginning to the end. And though many things ſeem unpoſſible unto men, yet with God all things are poſſible ſaith our bleſſed Saviour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Therefore it is poſſible that he ſhould foreſee all and every particular effect and occurrences from the beginning to the end; this you cannot deny it were abſurd if you ſhould. And you know likewiſe that <hi>The very hairs of our heads are numbred; and that a ſparrow falleth not to the ground with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the will of our heavenly Father.</hi> Which one would think were matters of too little moment for our wiſe Father to reckon up, or regard, and take notice of. But the reaſon is, he being om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipreſent and omniſcient and that eternally cannot poſſibly be ignorant of the leaſt occurrences that may poſſibly inſue. He being an infinite ſpirit, and all things being naked and open before him, and that from the very beginning, he declareth the end from the very beginning.</p>
            <p>He ſaith unto <hi>Job, Where waſt thou when I laid the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Earth? declare if thou hast underſtanding.</hi> See <hi>Job.</hi> 38.4.</p>
            <p>By which it appeareth that the Lord well knew and could alſo declare where the very materials of <hi>Job</hi> were of which he was compoſed: and that from the very beginning.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:29921:8"/>
            <p>And <hi>Job</hi> acknowledgeth alſo: I know that thou canſt do every thing, and that no thought can be hid from thee. Chap. 24.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nay he underſtandeth our thoughts long before we think them.</p>
            <p>The Lord foreſaw and diſcovered unto <hi>Moſes</hi> what the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael would do after his deceaſe, and therefore gave him a propheticall ſong to be a witneſs againſt them. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.16. &amp;c. to the 22. He knew their Imagination which they went about even then before he brought them into the land.</p>
            <p>But I ſhould hope that you would not ſtand in ſuch conceits and miſapprehenſions as to ſet bounds and limits to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and knowledge of God, which is infinite and unſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable, and his waies in ſome things paſt finding out.</p>
            <p>And if you will allow and do affirm with us that God was not ignorant what particular occurrences, both good and evill, ſhould happen unto all both Elect and Reprobates, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to the end: Then we muſt needs infer, and that from your own aſſentings, that they are quite contradictory to your own aſſentings.</p>
            <p>For you affirm page 1. particular the fourth, <hi>That the decrees of God concerning Election and Reprobation are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Immutable and unchangeable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ar.</hi> From which I argue.</p>
            <p>That if the Decree of God be unchangeable in reſpect of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection and Reprobation, And that from Eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Then it neceſſarily followeth; that he reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth none whom he decreed to elect; Nor electeth any whom he decreed to reprobate. Provided alwaies, that, as hath been ſaid, he was not ignorant of the particular perſons both of the Elect and Reprobates, and of all occurrences that ſhould enſue from the beginning to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ar.</hi> For if he was not ignorant of the particulars as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that we deny his omniſciency to be from eternity, and his underſtanding to be infinite, as hath been ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Then it is unpoſſible but his Decree and counſell and purpoſe of his will was perfect and compleat and clear in himſelf concerning every parricular both whom he would Elect
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29921:8"/>and whom he would reprobate: And this precedent, perfect, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate decree, being granted alſo to be abſolutely immutable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Then it is unpoſſible that any particular whom he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to Elect actually in time, ſhould become a Reprobate, nor any of thoſe whom he decreed to Reprobate, ſhould become his Elect.</p>
            <p>Which quite contradicteth your firſt particular, wherein you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from us about this head of doctrine, wherein you affirm that <hi>God hath not decreed from eternity to elect any perſon of mankind upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny terms, but that in caſe he liveth to years of diſcretion he may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly periſh, notwithſtanding any ſuch decree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the like arguments may be brought likewiſe againſt your 2d. particular, to wit,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That God hath not decreed from eternity the Reprobation of any perſon of mankind, conſidered as ſuch, who may not very poſſibly be ſaved, any decree in God notwithstanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much leſs do you hold a decree of Reprobation from Eternity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the farr greateſt part of mankind, excluding a poſſibility of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>For if you do aſſent <hi>That the decrees of God in theſe reſpects are abſolutely immutable and unchangeable:</hi> your aſſent herein is quite contradictory to your diſſenting, in this alſo, for the decree of God is as abſolute in the one as in the other, and as unchangeable like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>For his decrees ſhall ſtand, and he will do all his pleaſure, Yea, <hi>He will have mercy on whom he will have mercy, and whom he will he hardeneth, yea ſo many as he loves he will rebuke and chasten, and will give them repentance unto life that they may be ſaved; Yea, he will give them faith, for faith is the gift of God,</hi> Epheſ. 2.8. ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>For by grace ye are ſaved through faith, and that not of your ſelves, it is the gift of God.</hi> See verſe 9, 10. <hi>It is therefore of God that ſome repent and believe, and ſo are ſaved, and not of themſelves, nor for their good works, lest any man ſhould boaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But on the other part there are ſome others whom he blindeth and hardeneth, and ſhutteth or dulleth both their ears and hearts, <hi>leſt they ſhould repent and turn, and he ſhould heal them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though you think it ſo unjuſt and partial, and unequal, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo croſs or oppoſite to your rationalitie, and to the eſſentiall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29921:9"/>of God (as ſo you affirm page 81.) to wit,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is as a black thred of inconſistency with the attributes of God, to wit, his immutability, ſimplicity, wiſdome, grace, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, justice, and love to mankind;</hi> Inſomuch that though you are moſt vehemently and even paſſionately inclined to unity and peace with your brethren in matters of faith, yet are you not able with the beſt of your underſtandings to reconcile their doctrines in the points diſſented, with theſe glorious properties and perfections of our ever bleſſed God.</p>
            <p>Yet it doth not therefore follow but the wiſdome of God is able to convince you that theſe doctrines of your brethrens are fully and clealy reconcileable with theſe glorious properties and perfections of our bleſſed God.</p>
            <p>And what know you but God may poſſibly uſe ſome very mean, and unworthy inſtrument, to convince you of it, that ſo the whole glory of the diſpenſation of ſuch deep ſecrets might be given unto God, and not unto men.</p>
            <p>And therefore accounting of my ſelf both ſufficiently mean, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy and unlikely (as of my ſelf) for ſuch a buſineſs,</p>
            <p>And having formerly been of the ſame mind in which I think you are in ſome particulars conceming theſe points, and by the grace of God have receivd ſatisfaction &amp; full reſolution from the word of truth, I ſhall make bold, though but ſuch a man, to give you ſome hints how theſe glorious attributes of our bleſſed God may be fully cleared, and that to any rational apprehenſion in al theſe reſpects; If you pleaſe to read them with ſerious, mature, and deliberate conſideration, and with impartial minds, and a reſolution to act accordingly; for then you have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to know of the doctrine whether it be of God or but of humane invention.</p>
            <p>And this I ſhall indeavour as it pleaſeth God to give me utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>But according as you require I ſhall firſt follow you in your own reaſons and ſenſe which cauſeth you to diſſent in theſe particulars from your acknowledged brethren.</p>
            <p>Wherein I ſhall make it appear that theſe your reaſons ſtand in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect oppoſition againſt the wiſdome of God, Who can make it appear he is wiſer than men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. <hi>You ſay we judge that the threatnings of damnation in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29921:9"/>the ſcriptures to and againſt believers in caſe of apoſtacie, &amp;c. to be abſolutely inconſiſtent with a peremptory intent in God to ſave them, as Ezek.</hi> 18.24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.3. <hi>compared with verſe</hi> 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. <hi>compared with Rom.</hi> 1.6, 7, 8. <hi>And again you judge it a very ſenſeleſs part in a father to give his child a compleat aſſurance under hand and ſeal that he will make him his heir against all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble interveniencies whatſoever, And yet preſently threaten him if he be not dutifull to diſinherit him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, that you either in this therefore erre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you know not the Scriptures, nor the power of God, Or elſe you willfully oppoſe even the wiſdome of God, as accounting it fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>For you cannot but know that thus it is in the promulgation of the Goſpell. And that it is commanded, and ought to be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto all in generall, like a draw-net caſt into the Sea: And the promiſe and threatning to be preached together, and not ſingle by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; to wit, <hi>He that repenteth and believeth ſhall be ſaved, he that believeth not ſhall be condemned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this notwithſtanding that you know it thus commanded, yet in your wiſdome it is inconſiſtent with a peremptory decree to ſave ſome and to damn others; and you judge it a ſenſeleſs part in God, as in a Father, to give his children compleat aſſurance, and after threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to diſinherit them in caſe of diſobedience: As if you had quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten that it had ſo pleaſed him as by the fooliſhneſs of preaching to ſave them that believe, and whom he predeſtinates to the end, he alſo predeſtinates to the means. And thoſe who are kept by the power of God through faith unto ſalvation, yet he rebuketh and chaſteneth them, and threatneth them alſo if they be not obedient; yea, and deſerteth them alſo, &amp; hideth his face, as though he had forſaken them: And all this likewiſe after he hath given them aſſurance of eternal life through Jeſus Chriſt, as I hope you know, that after a full aſſurance in times of deſertion men may ſtand in doubt: it was ſo with <hi>David</hi> and many others; many eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bings and flowings in reſpect of ſtrength and weakneſs of faith there is found in all by ordinary experience. But to proceed, you in your judgement have already judged it a very ſenſeleſs part in a Father to give a child a compleat aſſurance under hand and ſeal, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar the 3d. you account of an enemy unto godlineſs, and that the reſult of it muſt needs make men remiſs, looſe, and indifferent in the ſervice of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29921:10"/>God, &amp;c. Whereas the wiſdome of God hath already judged it a means to make us more zealous and cordiall: and therefore it is that he giveth knowledge of ſalvation to his people by the remiſſion of their ſins, that they might ſerve him without fear in holineſs and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs all the daies of their lives. And fear hath torment in it, you know, and he that feareth is not yet perfect in love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> But we ought to endeavour to be perfect in love, and are bid alſo <hi>Fear not little flock, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Therfore it followeth, that in the wiſdom of God, &amp; through his love to his people, he would have them to attain perfection both in faith and love, See 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10, 11, 12, 13. yea even ſuch degrees whereby they might have ſtrong conſolation, and whereby their joy might be full, and therefore he biddeth them ask and they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it. And the <hi>Apostle John</hi> writeth unto them purpoſely that they might know that they have eternal life, and ſheweth them by what ſigns they may certainly know it; to wit, by their faith and love which God had given them: he that believeth on the ſonne of God ſaith he, hath the witneſs in himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Therefore it followeth, he that thus believeth can never pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, <hi>For who can pluck them out of the hands of God who is greater than all? and who can terminate an eternall life. And he that knoweth he believeth on the bleſſed name of the ſonne of God, and that loveth God, and loveth his brethren for their likeneſs unto God, may certainly know that he hath already this eternal life abiding in him, and that he ſhall never periſh. And by how much ſtronger confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence any man attains, and fuller aſſurance of faith, through the grace of God: By ſo much the more ſhall his love abound, and ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence his zeal in religion, and cordiallneſs in ſervice will be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>who will ſtrain and toil himſelf in run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for ſuch a prize which he knowes he ſhall as certainly obtain by going an eaſie, ſoft, and ordinary pace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, you ſpeak in this as though all Gods elect were at the firſt aſſured, and had no need to ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait gate, or to <hi>make their calling and election ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as though it were all one what degrees and meaſures of faith and holineſs we attain unto, and whether we be rich or poor, both in faith and good works.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:29921:10"/>
            <p>As though degrees of grace, and meaſures and multiplicity of good works and ſufferings, &amp;c. ſhould not add unto us a far more excellent and eternal weight of immortal glory.</p>
            <p>Whereas I know you know it, and will acknowledge there ſhall be great inequality of reward both to the Elect and Reprobates though nothing contradictious to juſtice or equality in reſpect of deſert: But ſuitable to their works according to their works, whether better or worſe, yea, more or fewer, as the Scripture is clear. And therefore I cannot but wonder to ſee you propoſe this as an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>For as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>They that run in a race run all, but one receiveth the prize.</hi> All Gods Elect may be ſaid to run, but not all alike for celeritie and attainments, <hi>ſome of the first ſhall be last, and ſome of the last ſhall be firſt, in reſpect of attainments to degrees and meaſures of faith and love, which are (eſſentially) in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for anſwer to your ſecond particular Reaſon, page 3. the which I over-skipped to anſwer the firſt and third both at once being one in ſubſtance, I onely anſwer thus much briefly, That they are very children in underſtanding that cannot refell this argument, to wit, that becauſe the decree of God hath ſo adjudged ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons to eternall life through Jeſus Chriſt, as ſo you know we affirm, that he hath <hi>choſen us in him before the foundation of the world was laid,</hi> and not peculiarly without him and his ſufferings, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Therefore yet you infer <hi>That ſuch an election is extremely inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to the death of Christ, and utterly diſſolveth the neceſſitie of it. Which cannot be reſented from ſuch knowing men, but as purpoſely intended to deceive the ſimple:</hi> You knowing the principles of all underſtanding men to be quite contrary, and too well fortifyed to be deceived with ſuch inconſequent aſſertions: For it is but thus much in effect, to wit,</p>
            <p>Becauſe in the preſcienceor foreknowledge and counſel of his will he hath choſen us in Chriſt, to be ſaved eternally through his death and ſufferings, and for his ſake: <hi>Ergo, Such ad Election is extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly injurious to the death of Christ, and utterly diſſolveth the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:29921:11"/>
            <p>How extremely injurious unto Rationality this argument is, I leave to all, yea, even Children of ten years of age, to judge the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I come now to anſwer your fourth Argument, where you bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirm, <hi>That ſuch a notion of Election layes the greateſt part of the neceſſity of preaching of the word in the very duſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, your Argument is a meer <hi>non ſequitur,</hi> for it is all but thus much, to wit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> Becauſe it hath pleaſed God to determine before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world to ſave thoſe that believe through the preaching of the word, and through Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> the preaching of the word, or to perſwade men to attend thereupon, is in vain and needleſs, for the Elect ſhall as certainly be ſaved, &amp;c. If they ſhould not do it.</p>
            <p>You have forgotten I ſuppoſe how <hi>Paul</hi> was inhibited to go unto ſuch a place becauſe they would not receive his doctrine, but was ſent unto another, and bid to <hi>ſpeak boldly, &amp;c. becauſe he had much people in that City:</hi> For you might know if ſuch Scriptures could down with you, <hi>That whom he foreknew, them he alſo predeſtinated to be conform'd to the image of his Son, and whom he predeſtinated them he alſo called, and whom he called them he alſo juſtified, and whom he justified them he alſo glorified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. In your fifth Argument you take upon you to argue directly, and bring a falſe ſlander upon the Wiſdome, Holineſs, Mercy and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God: For your Argument were good if rightly grounded. But your ground-work, which without all queſtion you take for granted, is manifeſtly untrue.</p>
            <p>For though all have ſinned, and are therefore deprived of the glory of God, and are only ſaved through Jeſus Chriſt, yea Jews <hi>by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture being Children of wrath as well as others,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet it doth not follow that all by nature are in their child-hood and minority alike ſinful, alike wrathful, or alike unclean, but in the ſight of God, and ſometimes of men likewiſe, there is great difference, though I muſt confeſs if any ask me who maketh thee to differ, and what haſt thou that thou haſt not received, I muſt acknowledge God himſelf hath done it.</p>
            <p>But this I affirm, and can make it manifeſt, that there was a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence even betwixt <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> in their Mothers Womb, Elſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29921:11"/>it had never been ſaid, <hi>I have loved Jacob, and have hated E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo the holy Ghoſt telleth us <hi>the wicked are eſtranged from the Womb, they go aſtray as ſoon as they be born, ſpeaking lies, &amp;c.</hi> and as <hi>Moſes</hi> hath teſtified, the efficient cauſe is not in God, but tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth us plainly <hi>They have corrupted themſelves, their ſpot is not the ſpot of his Children, they are a crooked and perverſe generation;</hi> they are perverſly generated; ſome generations of Vipers, ſome chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wickedneſs, becauſe ſpiritual wickedneſs was the productive cauſe of their generation; ſome ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> for Satan was the cauſe of their generation, and therefore though they were <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> children after the fleſh, yet our Saviour telleth them <hi>They were of their father the Devil, and would do his works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſome alſo are called <hi>Children of the fleſh</hi> in oppoſition to him that was born by promiſe, to wit, <hi>At ſuch a time will I come unto thee, and Sarah ſhall have a Son;</hi> The Lord himſelf was the chief cauſe of his generation, it was he that ſeparated him from the loines of his Parents, of free accord, whereas the devill, the world, or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fleſh was the cauſe of the begetting of ſome others, as hath been clearly ſhewed; but of this more fully in another place.</p>
            <p>But you may hereby ſee and be more cautious for ever after of bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the wiſdome and holineſs of God becauſe you ſee not how your ſelves forſooth can clear it up.</p>
            <p>You might as well have ſaid, <hi>If he have mercy on whom he will have mercy, and whom he will he hardeneth,</hi> he is doubtleſs unjuſt, unmerciful, unholy, unwife: which I for my part if I ſhould have ſaid it, it had been blaſphemous in me, but I hope you did it igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, and therefore upon repentance may find mercy.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To your ſixth I anſwer, That no man that ever I heard, ſpake of any more decrees of Election but one, yet there are ſo many particular actual elections as there are particular perſons Elected from the loins of their parents, as the chief cauſe of their generation, and this is their election when they are thus ſeparated to be veſſels of mercy prepared unto glory.</p>
            <p>But God is not the cauſe of the generation as chiefly predominant, but only permiſſive of the propagation of any children but his own E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</p>
            <p n="7">7. Your ſeventh I anſwer by way of Retortion or countercharge,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29921:12"/>That we do conceive that all the paſſages and texts of Scriptures which you produce and argue for the eſtabliſhment of your errours are meerly irrelative to ſuch a purpoſe, all them forced againſt their native and proper imports reſpectively to ſerve in this warfare, being all very ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of a more orthodox, fair, and Chriſtian interpretation than that which you make ſubſervient to your opinions.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To the eighth in like manner I retort, we can find no compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, indeed no tolerable ſatisfaction in any of thoſe arguments which you our brethren are wont to levie and inſiſt upon for the maintenance and Defence of your erronious doctrine; to wit, that there is no electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or decree of election of particular perſons as ſuch, but only of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire ſpecies of men from eternity; ſee your Arg. 9.</p>
            <p>But do judge in our ſouls and conſciences that through the grace of God we ſhall be enabled to give a Rational, fair, and Chriſtian account of their inſufficiency and weakneſs.</p>
            <p n="9">9. To the ninth I anſwer, that it hath more confirmed us in the truth, becauſe we find both from your pens and mouths, and that very frequently, ſuch very expreſſions as are palpable inconſiſtencies, and that your doctrine cumbreth and thwarteth plain texts of Scripture, and wholeſome neceſſary truths in Chriſtian Religion, and that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny orthodox and worthy doctrines cannot be pertinently nor effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mannaged if we receive the influence, and ſeek the aid, of this your principle, to wit, that there is no election or decree of election of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons as ſuch, but only of an intire ſpecies of men from eternity.</p>
            <p>For we affirm there is both, whereas your poſition denyeth the truth of theſe Scriptures, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4.11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.6.7.8. to 19. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. To the firſt argument for your diſſent in the ſecond particular, I anſwer, that we believe theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be really true, and that God doth intend as he here expreſſeth: &amp; we do believe, that however wicked men are by nature and by generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if God give them repentance unto life, ſo as that he doth ſave them, this is nothing elſe but what he had decreed before the foundation of the world, and that ſuch very perſons were choſen in Chriſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated to the adoption of Sons: And that he never intended to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate thoſe perſons, and therefore gave them repentance, and did not ſuffer them to obdurate and remain impenitent, nor doth any decree of his neceſſitate them or any other impulſively to continue in ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency; but permiſſively it doth, <hi>For he ſuffereth with long pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29921:12"/>the veſſels of warth fitted to deſtruction, Rom.</hi> 9. and that purpoſely to ſhew his wrath (againſt) and hatred (of) ſin, and to make his power known. And who are you that reply againſt God? as if his juſtice and mercy ſhould impell and neceſſitate the ſalvation of all, or elſe you will conteſt and quarrel againſt him as you do herein, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in your ſecond Reaſon, accounting it as a bowelleſs and mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Reprobation of the far greater part of mankind, which yet you cannot deny but the words of Chriſt himſelf import ſo much if we may believe him, <hi>Wide is the Gate, &amp;c. and many go in thereat:</hi> But in your apprehenſins theſe words of Chriſt are utterly inconſiſtent with thoſe pathetical, affectionate, and bowel-breathing wiſhes or deſires of God for the peace and proſperity even of the vileſt men, as you imagine; Whereas theſe were all ſpoken too and concerning his peculiar people; that they might have been happy, and their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities after them, if they had kept his commandments; and this he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after the manner of men; and if they had been obedient it had bin ſo with them; but we dare not conclude that God knew not before how they would carry and demean themſelves, for then we ſhould deny his underſtanding to be infinite: but theſe are ſpoken for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, and for our imitation, and there ſhould be in us ſuch like bowels &amp; earneſt deſires as there was in Chriſt conſider'd as man, to wit, that men would repent, and return and live; and they ought to perſwade what they can thereto, and ſuch who ſo do are inſtrumentall in the hand of God for the good of many, and ſhall doubleſs receive a reward ſuitable.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Your third Reaſon is in effect but the ſame with this, <hi>Intending to prove it as a brand of crueltie and folly if God ſhould reprobate his own, as the</hi> Oſtrich <hi>is cruell againſt her young ones.</hi> And to this I aſſent if he ſhould be cruel to his own elect, and that is all you can make of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Reaſon the fourth you proceed on in the ſame tone, replying and arguing againſt God, becauſe <hi>He doth reprobate the greatest part of men, as if becauſe we are lineally deſcended from the loins of</hi> Adam <hi>we were all alike by generation, and in alike meaſure children of wrath:</hi> which I have already anſwered that it is not ſo.</p>
            <p>And further I adde for your fuller conviction, that all reprobates are the natural off-ſpring, and fruit of ſin, and are the children of the wicked one, that is, the devil, in that reſpect: for it was the devil
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29921:13"/>that ſowed the tares, that is to ſay ſin, in the heats of our firſt parents, which have brought forth more tares, than the good ſeed, which was of God, and was left as a Remnant of the image of God in our firſt parents, hath yet produced; So that it is not proper to ſay of the wicked, <hi>that they are lineally deſcended from God, through the loines of</hi> Adam, <hi>who was his ſon;</hi> but were blaſphemous in me to ſpeak it; becauſe I thus apprehend and know it to be true.</p>
            <p n="5">5. You proceed, <hi>That all particular perſons of mankind without exception of any, were in</hi> Adam <hi>before his fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence you gather, <hi>If they were in him before his fall, they muſt be in the ſame ſtate, and condition of righteouſneſs and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with him; and conſequently of grace, favour and acceptance with God. Now we judge it clearly impoſſible that any perſon ſhould at the ſame time be in an eſtate of righteouſneſs or of grace and favour with God, and yet under a ſevere decree of Reprobation alſo, ſo that we cannot but conceive ſuch a decree of Reprobation from eternity as our brethren maintain, to be a meer and plain Impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, all mankind was originally in his loins, and he was made righteous, but they were not perſonally in him: But ſuppoſe it true, do not you conceive, that the Angells that ſinned, and are caſt down, and become devils, were created perfect and pure from ſin, and ſo in favour with God, whiles they ſo continued? yet were at that very time under a ſevere decree of eternall Reprobation; had not God decreed, and determined with himſelf, to ſuffer them to ſin, and fall as they did: and ſo in like manner, to ſuffer man alſo to be ſeduced by him, cannot you believe it, <hi>that his decrees are unchanga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> as you grant at the firſt, and that <hi>God acteth nothing, in time, but what he decreed from eternity;</hi> And that <hi>the Scripture expreſly holdeth forth, both a decree of Election, and a decree of Reprobati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in God,</hi> as you ſaid you <hi>agreed with your brethren in that,</hi> as in the 1.4.5. <hi>particulars?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whether then have your arguments lead you, that you here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it a plain Impoſſibility? ſo that the decree of God was nothing at all from eternity concerning Reprobation, either of Angels or men, though the Scripture telleth us, that ſome were of <hi>old ordained unto condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſome <hi>as natural brute beasts are made to be taken, and to be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29921:13"/>destroyed, ſpeaking evill of the things they underſtand not, and ſhall utterly periſh in their own corruption,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12.</p>
            <p>And let me but ask you, doth he not will now, what he willed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, even from eternity? is his will changed, or doth he will any thing now that he did not then? But ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>What if he willing to ſhew his wrath, and make his power known, ſuffer with long patience the veſſels of wrath fitted to deſtruction;</hi> But if theſe were the ends of <hi>ſuffering theſe veſſels,</hi> then it muſt needs follow that in the decree of God, he had this purpoſe in himſelf, as <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.9. where it is alſo ſaid verſe 11. <hi>That he worketh all things according to the Counſel of his own will;</hi> ſo that we cannot believe, that he either doth, or ſuffereth to be done, any thing at all, but <hi>according to the counſel of his own will:</hi> For he that could foreſee <hi>to predeſtinate</hi> ſuch who are his Elect, <hi>to the adoption of Children by Jeſus Christ in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf according to the Good pleaſure of his will,</hi> as <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.5. could not poſſibly be ignorant whom he ſhould <hi>harden</hi> unto condemnation. It were therefore wiſdome, if you could not comprehend the juſtneſs of his decree in this reſpect, yet not to make ſuch imperious and bold concluſions, whiles you cannot reconcile theſe you: ſubtill argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with theſe texts of Scripture; for all Scripture is true, and muſt not be broken, to comply with our fancies, and weak apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But Argument ſixth you ſpeak more boldly, for becauſe <hi>all things were in God, and in his will, and power, before he created them and made them viſible;</hi> Therefore you will needs make man, and not man only, but all things whatſoever, to be <hi>nothing really but God himſelf:</hi> according as you ſay <hi>it is a known maxim, whatſoever is in God is God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The which maxim in one ſenſe may be true, to wit, whatſoever is in God Attributably and Eſſentially is God: but it is well known that all things yet ſtill are really in God, but no creature can in any poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility be God himſelf, for every creature is ſomething elſe: and therfore I much wonder that a whole Church ſhould aſſert ſuch doctrine.</p>
            <p>And before the creation, when all things were in God, they were then no more God himſelf, than the dung that is contained in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal parts, of the bellie of man, is the man himſelf; And ſo by conſequence, notwithſtanding your bold Logick, God is no more <hi>the object of his own Reprobation, nor can no more be ſaid to reject
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29921:14"/>himſelf, or harden himſelf,</hi> than a man is ſaid to reject himſelf when he caſteth forth his moſt noiſome dung; and therefore I might well retort it upon you, that you knowing theſe things, and that ſome are rejected, and eternally damned, ſhould produce ſuch an argument, as if it did hold true, might induce the ignorant to blaſpeme the name of the lord our God, to their own deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To the ſeventh I anſwer that God doth not <hi>ſay unto all, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very perſon of mankind, If thou believeſt, thou ſhalt be ſaved:</hi> But as purpoſely revealing his decree, ſo far as he hath thought fit to let us know, his expreſſions are thus; <hi>He that repenteth and believeth ſhall be ſaved, and he that believeth not ſhall be condemned.</hi> So that your commiſſion is for both, and you ought to preach both, and not the one ſingle; for then you hide ſome part of <hi>the counſel of God:</hi> And ſo your <hi>Major</hi> being gone, your <hi>Minor</hi> fails, and is not worth anſwering.</p>
            <p n="8">8. This eighth argument, is the ſame in effect with the other, and no better grounded. It ſeems you are much offended, that the Goſpel muſt <hi>be preached unto all the world, and yet none but the Elect take hold of it by a lively faith, for their ſalvation;</hi> Now you it may be would be ſo wiſe, as to cull them forth, and tell them all plainly, you I have choſen, and you the reſt are Reprobates. Thus you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and reproach even the Wiſdome of God himſelf, and yet therin ſhew but your own folly: for if the Goſpel ſhould be preached peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly to the Elect, and they pointed out and diſtinguiſhed, &amp;c. how ſhould <hi>the rest be hardened?</hi> they would preſently deſpair; and how ſhould <hi>the Gospel be preached unto all nations for a witneſs againſt them,</hi> and to <hi>be unto them,</hi> as ſo God hath appointed it, <hi>the ſavor of death unto death,</hi> and a means to reſtrain them, &amp;c?</p>
            <p n="9">9. You <hi>judge our doctrine not to be a doctrine according to godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that it is moſt perniciously destructive to the interest and advancement of Godlineſs in the world:</hi> for firſt as you ſay <hi>it preſents the Gospel unto men like a Lottery, wherin are many blanks, but few prizes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that if you be ſo ſober, and conſiderate, as not to <hi>meddle with it, nor adventure upon it,</hi> till you make it good, That <hi>all that hear it are Gods Elect, and ſhall certainly be ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is very doubtfull you will reject ſalvation, and come ſhort of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29921:14"/>but if you can make it out, it is a comfortable doctrine; they deſerve to give you treble <hi>honour</hi> to our beſt Doctors.</p>
            <p>And as for anſwer to your ſecond caſe, we do not uſe to perſwade men they are Reprobates <hi>upon every declining or miſcarriage,</hi> for then we ſhould teach it in this caſe to you, who in theſe reſpects have declined the truth, but we apply unto them ſuch <hi>precious promiſes wherby we our ſelves have been comforted of God,</hi> when Satan hath ſuggeſted ſuch like doctrines into our minds <hi>to destroy our faith,</hi> as theſe of yours, to wit, <hi>that notwithstanding our Election, yet we may poſſibly periſh:</hi> And the truth is, that theſe and ſuch like arguments, <hi>if it were poſſible, they might deceive even the very elect,</hi> but they <hi>are kept by the power of God through faith unto ſalvation,</hi> bleſſed be his name, and can <hi>never periſh, neither can any pluck them out of his hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. You <hi>judge alſo that ſuch a decree of Reprobation is diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trally repugnant to all thoſe bleſſed Manifestoes or Declarations made by God himſelf of the riches of his Grace, Mercy, Love, Kindneſs, Goodneſs, Compaſſion, Patience, Long-Suffering, Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty unto the world.</hi> See <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6, 7. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 8.15.111.4. <hi>Job</hi> 3.16. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.8, 9. <hi>to omit other places without number.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have ſearched theſe Scriptures, but find no repugnancie in them againſt our doctrine, but I find in the firſt, <hi>Exodus</hi> 34.6, 7. That as God is <hi>merciful and gratious, long ſuffering, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in goodneſs and truth, keeping mercy for thouſands, forgiving i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquitie and tranſgreſſion and ſin;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So alſo that he <hi>will by no means clear the guilty, but viſiteth the iniquities of the Fathers upon the children, and upon the childrens children unto the third and fourth generation.</hi> See alſo for this <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.18, 19. ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.20, 21, 22. though you will ſtorm and fret at this, as unjuſt in God, who is able to anſwer you, and will one day, yea and clear it to be juſt, notwithſtanding all your Logick, and that to your own conſciences; though now for the preſent you are dark in the buſineſs, how it can be juſt to viſit, &amp;c. of which more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in its due place.</p>
            <p n="11">11. You ſay in your eleventh reaſon, <hi>That you cannot find any mention, nor the leaſt intimation of any ſuch decree of Reprobation in the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:29921:15"/>
            <p>To which I anſwer, I am ſorry to hear that a whole Church ſhould be ſo ignorant of the Scriptures, and ſo well vers'd in humane do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, injuriouſly wreſted from ſome particular places, which were never intended for ſuch a ſenſe: you are not herein like the noble <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However I ſhall ſpeak unto you in Scripture language, but I will not cite the places to you, I hope you know it is contained in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>That he worketh all things according to the counſell of his will, and that his counſell ſhall stand, and he will do all his pleaſure;</hi> yea, <hi>He hath mercy on whom he will, and whom he will he hardeneth;</hi> yea, ſome are ſaid to be <hi>of old ordained unto condemnation,</hi> and <hi>as brute beasts are made to be taken and to be deſtroyed;</hi> And <hi>he made all things for himſelf, yea, even the wicked for the day of evil;</hi> for he hath <hi>power,</hi> and juſtly too, as <hi>the Potter of his clay,</hi> to <hi>make one veſſel unto honour, and another unto diſhonour,</hi> and that of the ſame clay; ſuch whom he maketh as <hi>veſſels of wrath unto diſhonour,</hi> he maketh on purpoſe that <hi>he may ſhew his wrath:</hi> and he is able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it upon what accompt he maketh ſuch veſſels, and to convince the conſciences of all men whomſoever that it is but juſt, and will one day do it, againſt all their cavils, ſo as <hi>every mouth ſhall be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped:</hi> for ſhall we think it poſſible, but he that is <hi>the Judge of all the world ſhould do right?</hi> it were abſurd to think it. You ſay you <hi>Gather by many things comming from them occaſionally, That your brethren would willingly enough let go their doctrine of Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation if they knew how to retain their doctrine of Election without it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It may well be that your brethren would not much ſtrive with you about this doctrine, if they could help it; though they know it is true. But if you cannot teach them, how it is poſſible that this <hi>Doctrine of Election,</hi> which is very clear from expreſs Scriptures, can poſſibly chuſe, but muſt neceſſarily draw after it this premiſed <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Reprobation,</hi> they will acknowledge you to be far more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional than any of them.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>We clearly and very frequently find</hi> (you ſay) <hi>both in the writings and oral diſcourſes of the Patrons of the ſaid decree of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, ſuch ſayings and paſſages which we know not how to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile with this decree, and conſequently cannot but judge ſuch a decree to be very diſharmonious to the true ſtrains and doctrins of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:29921:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The beſt patronage we have for it, is the word of God; and it is all that we dare cleave too, to make it out.</p>
            <p>But if your conſequence and judgement be groundedly raiſed, to wit, <hi>That our doctrines are not harmonious with the Goſpel,</hi> then upon the ſame ground we may paſs our judgement infallibly upon yours.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For as hath been ſhewed, you firſt agree with us that <hi>The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture expreſly holdeth forth and aſſerteth both a decree of Election and a decree of Reprobation in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And that <hi>theſe decrees were in God from Eternity or before the foundatiens of the world were laid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And that <hi>both theſe decrees as well as all others attributable to God, are really and ſimply God himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And that <hi>theſe decrees as all others in God are like God himſelf abſolutely immutable and unchangeable, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then in your very firſt particular of your diſſent from us, you quite contradict what you aſſented to, as hath been argued before, and repreſent unto us the counſel and decree of God, as changeable as the Moon, or as the mind of man, as if the counſel of God were wholly dependent on the will of man, as if the wiſdome of God were not perfect and full for making his decrees abſolute, till he receive inſtructions from the actings of men how he ſhould judge them; you ſay <hi>it is poſſible, notwithſtanding his Decree of Election,</hi> that <hi>his Elect ſhould periſh, and notwithstanding his Decree of Reprobation of any particular perſon, yet he may poſſibly be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we ſhall freely accord, that ſome particular perſons, which you or we think to be his Elect may poſſily periſh, or whom we think to be Reprobates, may poſſibly be ſaved.</p>
            <p>But to avouch it poſſible, that the Decree of God, concerning par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, is changeable, We dare not do it, unleſs you can aſſure us that he did not foreſee from the beginning, who ſhould be ſaved, and who ſhould periſh.</p>
            <p>But all <hi>his ſheep,</hi> all his <hi>Elect,</hi> are <hi>choſen in</hi> Chriſt <hi>before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world, that they ſhould be holy and without blame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in love, Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. and they are <hi>alſo predestinate to be conformed to the Image of his ſonne:</hi> Theſe all being the <hi>Sheep</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>hear his voice, and he knoweth them, and they follow him, and he giveth unto them eternal liſe, and they ſhall never periſh, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29921:16"/>ſhall any man pluck them out of his hand, his father who gave hem to him is greater than all, and no man is able to pluck them out of his fathers hand; And he and his father are one.</hi> See <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.27, 28, 29, 30.</p>
            <p>And all the reaſon that Chriſt renders why others <hi>believed not,</hi> is becauſe they were <hi>not his ſheep,</hi> verſe 26. they were none of his Elect.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Now your third particular head of doctrine, wherin you ſay you diſſent from us, is,</p>
            <p>That <hi>God hath not decreed the Reprobation of any infant, dying before the commiſſion of actual ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, I was once of your mind in this particular, and was ſo perſwaded upon the ſame grounds that you here hold forth.</p>
            <p>But through the grace of God was long ſince reſolved that it was not true.</p>
            <p>Firſt I thought as in your fourth reaſon, <hi>That the caſe of all infants dying before the commiſſion of actual ſin to be one and the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I apprehended they were all alike, and in a like meaſure by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture children of wrath one as well and as much as another,</hi> and ſo either all ſaved or all damned.</p>
            <p>But I could not believe they were all damned for ſuch like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as you here allege, therefore I concluded, they were certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaved.</p>
            <p>But upon better conſideration, as it pleaſed God to give me to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that though Jews <hi>by nature were children of wrath as well as Gentiles, which is the proper ſcope of that expreſſion, Epheſ.</hi> 2.3. as will appear by the context, and not that every particular child, is by nature alike, and in the ſame meaſure polluted with ſin, but though all were polluted in the ſight of God, Chriſt himſelf excepted, yet there was great difference and diſparitie amongſt them in the ſight of God, which put me quite into another mind, and ſearching the Scriptures, I was preſently confirmed quite the contrary. I ſhall therefore hold forth ſuch Scriptures and reaſons, as confirmed me, and gave me full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves in any queſtion that could be propoſed concerning this doctrine of Election and Reprobation.</p>
            <p>And firſt then for proof, that all children when new born, are not in the ſame meaſure fleſh, nor alike fleſhly, nor that they are all alike,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29921:16"/>and in the ſame meaſure ſinful; or veſſels of wrath, or in the State of wrath, nor alike beloved or hated of God, nor alike unclean or clean in his ſight. It will evidently appear from the word of God: Though I do not ſay I can make this difference appear unto men, whiles they are unborn, yet it will appear that there is then ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As firſt I argue; If God loveth one thing and hateth another, there is certainly a difference, and diſparity, betwixt thoſe things, in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> For he loveth the good, and hateth the evil, and cannot both hate and love the very ſelf ſame thing; nor as he cannot chuſe but hate the evil, ſo he cannot but love, whatever is good, for <hi>every good proceedeth of God.</hi> And it were no leſs than blaſphemie, to ſay he loveth the evil, or hateth the good, as it may well be ſaid of ſome wicked men who alwaies do ſo.</p>
            <p>Nor we may not ſay, that the love or hatred of our wiſe God, is without a cauſe, and that juſt and clear, to his own comprehenſion, though not ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſſum.</hi> But he <hi>loved Jacob and hated Eſau when they were in the womb, and had neither of them done either good or evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq. Ergo,</hi> there was <hi>difference</hi> in the ſight of God, when they were in the womb, one was then <hi>a veſſel of wrath</hi> in fitting <hi>for destruction,</hi> and the other was doubtleſs <hi>a veſſel of mercy in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. If children were all alike by nature after their propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation from the loines of their parents, and that there were <hi>no differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> (but as all are polluted and all are defiled, either leſs or more, Chriſt himſelf excepted) ſo all were alike polluted and a like defiled, by means of generation, being <hi>conceived in iniquitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> 1. Then it would follow, that the <hi>juſt Lord,</hi> who <hi>will doe no iniquity,</hi> and who is <hi>Judge of all the World, ſhould not doe right,</hi> In <hi>viſiting the iniquities of the fathers upon the children, unto the third and fourth generation of them that hate him; And ſhewing mercy unto thouſands, to them that love him, and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> 2. And then it would likewiſe follow, that it were all one, and no greater diſparagement to be <hi>the children of fooles, and children of baſe men, that are viler than the earth,</hi> than the proper ſeed of ſuch
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29921:17"/>as <hi>love God, and keepe his Commandements.</hi> See <hi>Job</hi> 30.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conjeq.</hi> 3. And then it would follow, that the Apoſtle ſaid not true when he ſaid, <hi>Elſe your children were uncleane, but now are they holy,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14, If it be ſo, that all children being new borne be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>uncleane,</hi> or alike <hi>holy,</hi> and in the ſame meaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> 4. And then it would follow, that it is all one whether <hi>we poſſeſſe our veſſels in holineſſe and in honour, or in the luſt of concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, like ſuch as know not God;</hi> If by that meanes, our ſeed when propagated, ſhould not be the better, and the more <hi>holy and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> in the ſight of God. See 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.4, 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> 5. It would follow, that there were <hi>unrighteouſneſſe with God</hi> in that fevere excluſion of <hi>Ammonites, and Moabites, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards likewiſe, from entring into the congregation of the Lord, to their tenth generation.</hi> Deur. 23.2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> 6. Then it were all one to be as <hi>Iſhmael, borne after the fleſh;</hi> as to be borne as <hi>Iſaac, a child of promiſe;</hi> to wit, <hi>At ſuch a time will I come unto thee, and</hi> Sarah <hi>ſhall have a ſonne.</hi> See <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.23, 28. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8, 9. <hi>Gen:</hi> 18.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> 7. Then it would follow, that the <hi>fruits</hi> and operations <hi>of the Spirit,</hi> are all alike good, in the ſight of God, with the <hi>fruits,</hi> and effects, and operations <hi>of the fleſh,</hi> if we muſt expect to reape the ſame fruits, or the like effects. And then it is no matter of <hi>walking in the ſpirit, that we might not fulfill the luſts of the fleſh.</hi> And ſo <hi>adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, fornication, uncleanneſſe, laſciviouſneſſe, evill concupiſcence, and inordiuate affections, are all one in effect with love, joy, peace, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meekneſſe, temperance;</hi> as <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, &amp;c. to 13. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5, 6. Then it were all one to <hi>walke after the ſpirit,</hi> or to be <hi>drawn away by our owne luſts, and entiſed; and ſo when luſt hath conceived,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi>) <hi>it bringeth forth ſinne; and ſinne when it is finiſhed bringeth forth death:</hi> whereas <hi>every good gift, and every perfect gift, cometh from above,</hi> Jam. 1.14, 15, 16, 17. and Chap. 3.17. Whereas all other affections are but from beneath, <hi>earthly, ſenſuall, or deviliſh,</hi> verſ. 15. Yea then it is all one to <hi>ſow to the fleſh as to the ſpirit;</hi> yea to make <hi>proviſion for the fleſh to fulfill the luſts thereof,</hi> as to <hi>ſow to the ſpirit,</hi> if we may expect the ſame <hi>fruits,</hi> Gal. 6.6. And ſo all theſe Scriptures untrue and vaine. See alſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. to 15.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29921:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> 8. Then it would follow, that it might as properly be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Elect, as of the wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.3, 4; 5. to wit, <hi>The wicked are eſtranged from the wombe, they goe aſtray as ſoone as they be borne, ſpeaking lyes. Their poyſon is as the poyſon of aſerpent; they are like the deafe adder that ſtoppeth her eare, which will not hearken to the voyce of charmers, charming never ſo wiſely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> 9. And ſo by conſequence we may pray as <hi>David,</hi> againſt not onely the wicked, but all mankind; to wit, <hi>Breake their teeth O God, &amp;c.</hi> verſ. 6, 7, 8. and propheſy as <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. How <hi>ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly they ſhall be deſtroyed, at which the righteous ſhall rejoyce;</hi> as <hi>verſ.</hi> 10, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> 10. Then it would follow, that all generations are alike, and have the ſame ſpot, or ſtampe and temper of ſpirit; contrary to that text, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.5. to wit, <hi>They have corrupted themſelves, their spot is not the spot of his children, they are a perverſe and crooked ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</hi> And contrary to thoſe various expreſſions of the ſorts of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations that we reade of in Scripture; as <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.11. to wit,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a generation that curſeth their father, and that doth not bleſſe their mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a generation that are pure in their owne eyes, and yet is not waſhed from their filthineſſe,</hi> v. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a generation, Oh how lofty are their eyes, and their eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lids are lifted up,</hi> v. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a generation whoſe teeth are as ſwords, and their jaw-teeth as knives, to destroy the poor from off the earth, and the needy from among men,</hi> v. 14.</p>
            <p>And contrary to our ordinary experience, as for the moſt part it is: for though godly parents may have ſome prophane children, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane parents may have ſome godly children; yet for the moſt part, as the Scripture ſpeakes, it is found by experience, that <hi>like father like ſonne, like mother like daughter:</hi> For by generation their like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is ſtamped, or propagated from them, in the very ſeed of generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo that generations of <hi>vipers</hi> are a viperous brood; and therefore <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt wondred much, <hi>who had forew arned ſuch to fly from the wrath to come;</hi> And <hi>an evill and an adulterous generation,</hi> are an evill and an adulterous brood: and therefore was that though they <hi>ſought a ſigne, there ſhould be no ſigne given unto them, but the ſigne of the Prophet</hi> Jonas.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29921:18"/>
            <p>And againe, ſome are called <hi>children of wickedneſſe,</hi> becauſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe was predominant, and the chiefe cauſe of their generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>And ſome againe are called <hi>children of the Devill, ſonnes of Belial,</hi> and are therefore ſaid to be <hi>of their father the Devill</hi> by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, though of the Jewiſh nation; and therefore Chriſt told them plainly, they did and would <hi>doe their fathers workes or lusts,</hi> John 8.44. and 1 John 3.8. <hi>He that committeth ſinne is of the Devill:</hi> Cain <hi>was of the wicked one, and ſlew his brother,</hi> v. 12.</p>
            <p>And on the other part, ſome are called, <q rend="inline">An holy generation, a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen generation, the generation of the Juſt which ſhall be bleſſed; the off-ſpring of God, a righteous ſeed, a ſeed left us as a remnant, when others are deſtroyed; yea a ſeed which the Lord hath bleſſed, and of whom he teſtifieth, that he formed them from the wombe, and that he will helpe them, and that he will poure his Spirit upon their ſeed, and his bleſſing upon their off-ſpring, and they ſhall ſpring up as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the graſſe, as willowes by the water-courſes: One ſhall ſay, I am the Lords, and another ſhall call himſelfe by the name of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and another ſhall ſubſcribe with his hand unto the Lord, and ſimame himſelfe by the name of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Iſa. 44.3, 4, 5.</q> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> was no ſooner borne, but <hi>David</hi> by the Spirit of prophecy <hi>called his name</hi> Jadidiah, <hi>becauſe the Lord loved him;</hi> and whom he loves once, he loves to the end. He ſaith allſo to <hi>Ieremiah, Before I formed thee in the wombe I knew thee, and before thou cameſt out of the wombe I ſanctified thee, &amp;c.</hi> Jerem. 1. and <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt <hi>was filled with the Holy Ghost in his mothers womb, and ſprang in her womb at the voyce of</hi> Mary <hi>for gladneſſe of ſpirit.</hi> And the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, though he was perfect man, and borne of fleſh in ſome reſpect: yet in reſpect of his ſpirit, or mind, or qualification, he was the Lord from heaven, and that allſo when he was in the wombe, and had notacted as man either good or evill.</p>
            <p>And give me leave to aske you: Is it all one, and may we poſſibly expect as godly a ſeed, if the ſonnes of God ſhalt take them wives of the daughters of men, or of the daughters of <hi>Heth,</hi> or daughters of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> infidels, unclean, unholy, unrighteous, ſuch as are haters of God. See <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.2. and 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14.15, 16, 17, 18. and 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 7.14, 15. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5?</p>
            <p>As if they take them wives of a quite contrary temper, diſpoſition,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29921:18"/>and carriage, ſuch as are holy and honourable, faithfull and virtuous, loving and amiable, of a meeke and quiet ſpirit, which in the ſight of the Lord is a thing much ſet by.</p>
            <p>Is there not plaine expreſſions quite contradictory each to other? To wit,</p>
            <p>The generation of the juſt ſhall be bleſſed, but the name of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhall rot, <hi>Prov.</hi> 
               <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.20. The ſeed of evill doers ſhall never be renowned for ever: and therefore it is ſaid, Prepare a ſlaughter for his children for the iniquity of their parents, that they doe not riſe up, nor poſſeſſe the land, nor fill the face of the world with ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; or as in our tranſlation, with (enemies.) Who can expect, but that the proper fruit, or children of ſuch parents, ſhould likewiſe fill up the meaſure of their parents; or ſuch as are ſerpents, generations of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, ſhould poſſibly eſcape the damnation of hell. See <hi>Mat.</hi> 31.32, 33.</p>
            <p>From all which I argue: If ſome be holy, and ſome be unholy, when they are in the ſeed; and that in the very wombe, when they have not done either good or evill, and are therefore accordingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved or hated;</p>
            <p>Then it neceſſarily followeth, that there is great diſparity, and a vaſt difference when they are in the wombe, and have not done either good or evill; much more then, when they are come to more maturity, and are brought forth allſo; for as they grow in ripeneſſe, they grow in difference; and to be briefe and plaine, the difference is ſo great, as hath beene clearly ſhewed, that ſome are properly ſonnes of God, through Jeſus Chriſt, whilſt they are in the wombe; and ſome are as properly the ſonnes of <hi>Belial:</hi> for as the firſt are begotten through the powerfull operation of the Spirit of God, ſanctifying the minds and affections of parents, and giving them grace, and affections ſuitable for generation, and to poſſeſſe their veſſels in holineſſe and in honour, and ſo their ſeed is holy in a great meaſure, in the ſight of God, through his owne grace. So on the other part, the other are begotten through the powerfull operations of the Devill, the World, and their owne corrupt and fleſhly deſires, which by the infligation of him that ruleth in the aire, and in the children of diſobediee, are kindled and enflamed with deſires and affections, wicked and perverſe, and ſuch as are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy in the ſight of God, poſſeſſing their veſſels in the luſt of concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, as hath beene ſaid: So their very ſeed is polluted and uncleane
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29921:19"/>in the ſight of God, when they have not done either good or evill; as <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, If thoſe that are thus wicked and uncleane before him, ſhall be by any meanes perſwaded to repent and turne from ſuch their wickedneſſe, and dee that which is lawfull and right before him, they ſhall ſurely live; for the Lord hath teſtified, he deſireth not the death even of him that dieth, nor hath no pleaſure in it, but rather that he ſhould repent and live. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.30. and <hi>Philemon</hi> v. 10, 19. and <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.19, 20. and verſe 16, 17, 18. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. So that it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they may be converted, and repent, and live. Though it cannot be denied, but God hath determined whom he will ſave, and whom he will condemne; for ſo ſaith the Scripture, His underſtanding is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.11, 12. to 20. Therefore he cannot be ignorant whom he hath elected, and whom he will harden: But this counſell is ſecret, and ought not by us to be determined, till it manifeſtly appeare by ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and fiuits, as we can diſcover by the Word of God, and by the ſacred teſtimony of his holy Spirit, which doubtleſſe will witneſſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with our owne ſpirits, at one time or other, ere we depart this life, that we are ſonnes of God, if we be his Elect, and then we are ſure we ſhall never periſh: But this ſacred teſtimony may be kept backe till our laſt houre, and yet we may be ſaved; and therefore we ought not to deſpaire, whileſt we have our breath, neither of our ſelves, nor others: but muſt conſider, that as his underſtanding, ſo his mercy and juſtice are both infinite, and kiſſe each other, according to equity and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            <p>In your fourth Reaſon of your diſſent from us, in your third par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, you ſay,</p>
            <q>
               <p>That ſome Infants, dying in their infancy, your brethren them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves acknowledge to be Elect, and ſo conſequently ſaved: Now, ſay you, we knowing,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The juſt and mercifull God to be no accepter of perſons.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The caſe of all Infants, as well to matter of righteouſneſſe, as of ſinne, or guilt of ſinne, to be the ſame.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And laſtly, That as well remiſſion of ſinnes, and the ſalvation of perſons thereupon, as the retaining of ſinnes, and condemnation upon it, to be judiciary acts of God, proceeding from him as a moſt righteous Judge, cannot but conceive, that if ſome Infants, dying In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, be ſaved, the ſame muſt needs the condition be of all.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:29921:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, That it evidently appeareth that all your whole doctrine wherein you diſſent from us, in all your five particulars, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth chiefly upon one pinne, wherein all the fallacy of your whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke is dependant: the which pinne being once proved a fallacy, and ſo broken off as a meer device of mans braine, and no Scripture truth, all your whole fabricke falls to the ground: and therefore it is, that I have chiefly encountered with this one falſe principle, and let the moſt part of your other diſſentings alone, till I ſee the effect of what is here exhibited: Expecting that when you ſee this principle removed, you will eaſily anſwer all your owne Reaſons and Arguments exhibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt us in your owne minds, and ſave me a labour: However, if you put me to it, I ſhall doe it hereafter, but for the preſent I avoid, as much as is poſſible, <hi>all Impertinencies,</hi> as ſo you requeſted me in your Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>Now your falſe principle, which it may be you take for granted by all your brethren; and whether they hold it or no, I ſhall not now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute: But I for my part utterly deny it; and all the conſequences you deduce from it is this, to wit,</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>We knowing that the caſe of all Infants, as well to matter of righteouſneſſe, as oſ ſinne, or guilt of ſinne, to be the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For removall of which principle, I have ſhewed in the booke many abſurd conſequences that would neceſſarily follow: Take theſe two more as ſufficient of themſelves to any rationall apprehenſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Arg.</hi> That if the caſe of all Infants were the ſame in reſpect of righteouſneſſe or ſinne;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Then it would follow, that all children ſo ſoone as they are children, are either all beloved or all hated of God, and ſo all ſaved or all damned when ever they dye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For whom he loveth once, he loveth to the end; for he is not changeable in his love or hatred, as I hope you believe: And ſo whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they live to yeares of diſcretion or no, whom he once loveth cannot poſſibly periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. That if all Infants were the ſame, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Then it would follow, that <hi>Iſaac, Jacob, Jeremiah, John</hi> Baptiſt, yea and even Chriſt himſelfe, were no holier in the wombe than <hi>Iſhmael, Eſay, Cain,</hi> and the two ſonnes of <hi>Elie, Hophnie</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas,</hi> and all ſuch like, who being <hi>wicked,</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>eſtranged from the wombe, and to goe aſtray as ſoone as they be borne, ſpeaking
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29921:20"/>lyes; whoſe poyſon is as the poyſon of a ſerpent, and they like the deafe adder that will not hearken to the voyce of charmers charming never ſo wiſely,</hi> Pſal. 58.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>Whereas on the other part, <hi>Iſaac</hi> was a child of promiſe, ſeparated by the hand of God, <hi>At ſuch a time will (I) come unto thee, and</hi> Sarah <hi>ſhall have a ſonne.</hi> And <hi>Jacob</hi> was beloved oſ God when in his mothers wombe. And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was ſanctified before he came forth of the wombe. And <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt was filled with the Holy Ghoſt from his mothers wombe. And Chriſt himſelfe with the bleſſed Deity, as the only qualification of his humane ſoule.</p>
            <p>And therefore it muſt needs follow,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> That there is difference in the ſight of God in the very wombe, and ſome are beloved, and ſome hated; and this love &amp; hatred <hi>are like God himſelfe, abſolutely immutable and unchangeable,</hi> as ſo you grant in your fourth particular, pag. 1.</p>
            <p>And againe, from the ſame principle you further <hi>hold,</hi> not only <hi>that all perſons without exception are put into an actuall poſſeſſion of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God, by his grace in the gift of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which poſſeſſion they ſtill keepe during Infancy, and untill the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Actuall ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But further, That all men living to yeares of diſcretion, and moſt eſpecially whiles they have not fouly corrupted, or wretchedly hardned themſelves, by long continuance in waies of knowne ſinnes, are by the ſame grace put into a good capacity of ſalvation: So that if they be not wanting to themſelves, and this in a very groſſe, palpable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy manner, they may by the grace of God vouchſafed unto them, come to repent and believe, and perſevere, believing unto ſalvation.</hi> See your 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Reaſon of diſſenting in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> head of doctrine.</p>
            <p>This and the former laid together, include, that all children (whiles in Infancy) till they come to yeares of diſcretion, are put into an actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all poſſeſſion of the favour of God; and this they all keepe during In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy; and they are all alike as to matter of ſinne or righteouſneſſe, none hath more ſinne in them than another, nor any more righteouſneſſe than another; And ſo by conſequence,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> They are all alike beloved of God in Chriſt Jeſus, and all alike hated in reſpect of ſinne, which is of all other the greateſt abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity: But I returne you backe to what hath beene ſaid.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:29921:20"/>
            <p>Again, you affirm, pag. 11. Rea. 5. of your diſſent in the third particular:</p>
            <p>That <hi>you know not how to reconcile the tormenting of millions of poor Infants, who never provoked God by any actuall ſinne, with that Philanthropy, thoſe tender mercies, bowels and compaſſions, that great propenſion and readineſſe to pardon, which the Scriptures ſo frequent, and with ſuch expreſſeneſſe of words, depredicate in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, That it ſeems to me you cannot reconcile the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and ſeverity of God with his infinite Mercy: Yet if I might ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you, I ſhould account it your wiſedome not to make too perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Concluſions upon ſuch Premiſes, leſt your own weakneſſe in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and comprehenſion in ſuch caſes, be found to be the cauſe why you cannot make this reconciliation betwixt Infinite Juſtice, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Mercy; for without all queſtion they are reconcileable, though you cannot doe it.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, you know, that <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah, and the Cities about them, are ſet forth for an example, ſuffering the vengeance of eternall fire.</hi> Jude verſ. 7.</p>
            <p>This was an example of his ſevere juſtice; I cannot find but all their children in thoſe Cities doe ſuffer <hi>the vengeance of eternall fire.</hi> And if they doe ſo, then I hope you will not deny but it is juſt, for <hi>the juſt Lord will doe no iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though I will not undertake to determine, that all their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſo the children of <hi>Corah and his company, that went down quick into the pit, doe ſuffer the vengeance of eternall fire;</hi> for it is a ſecret: yet you cannot prove that any were ſaved that were ſo deſtroy'd in his fierce wrath; nor can you ever prove that any that periſhed in the floud were ſaved, when he brought in the floud upon the world of the ungodly.</p>
            <p>But this is evident, that <hi>God viſiteth the iniquities of the fathers even upon the children, and that to the third and fourth generation of them that hate him:</hi> That is to ſay, He looketh upon the iniquities of the fathers, as it were ſtamped on their children; for their likeneſſe being ſtamped or impreſt on their children, by means of generation, he looketh on them, and accounteth of them, ſo ſoon as ever they be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, to be vile, and odious, and abominable in his ſight, and hateth them even then, as he did <hi>Eſay,</hi> when they are in the wombe; ſo that whether they live to years of diſcretion or no, it is all one; for if he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29921:21"/>once hate them, as that he muſt needs doe, if they be the off-ſpring of Satan, or of ſpirituall wickedneſſe, I doe not ſee but they muſt needs periſh, though they dye in infancy:</p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>the off-ſpring</hi> of God, ſuch whom he ſeparateth from the loynes of their parents by means of generation, when ever they dye they are certainly ſaved, for <hi>he loveth the works of his own hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And without all peradventure it may be ſaid of ſome, as <hi>Job</hi> 10.10, 11, 12. <hi>He hath powred them forth like milk, and crudled them like cheeſe, and cloathed them with skin and fleſh, and fenced them with bones and ſinews; he hath granted them life and favour, and his viſitation hath preſerved their ſpirits.</hi> And though theſe things be ſecret unto men, yet <hi>Job</hi> knew, <hi>that it was thus with God,</hi> v. 13. and therefore accounted himſelf peculiarly <hi>the work of his own hands,</hi> in direct oppoſition to thoſe that are wicked: See verſ. 3, 7, 8, 9. and that from this very ground, <hi>Is it good,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, that thou ſhouldeſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, that thou ſhouldeſt deſpiſe the work of thine hands, and ſhine upon the counſell of the wicked? Thou knoweſt that I am not wicked, and there is none that can deliver out of thine hand. Thy hands have made me and faſhioned me together round about.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, Thou haſt taken pains about me, even in my very generation, whereas it cannot be ſaid that thou doſt ſo to the wicked, and therefore theyare not ſo peculiarly thine own workmanſhip: they cannot be called <hi>a holy generation, a righteous ſeed, a ſeed reſerved of God, the off-ſpring of God, a choſen generation,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. as hath been ſpecified before: It is more proper to call them <hi>generations of vipers, evill and adulterous generations, children of wickedneſſe, ſons of Belial,</hi> yea even <hi>veſſels of wrath</hi> made on purpoſe <hi>for the day of evill, made to be taken and to be deſtroyed:</hi> Even as men ſometimes make veſſels for retention of noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, unclean and filthy things, that ſo they may caſt them forth, both veſſell and all, out of their ſight and preſence.</p>
            <p>For juſt ſo it is, God maketh the veſſels for retention of wrath, or <hi>spirituall wickedneſſe,</hi> which by means of generation is propagated together with the ſeed of generation from the very loyns of parents: Which though we are not able to diſtinguiſh, nor diſcern the nature of <hi>spirituall wickedneſſe,</hi> nor how it is propagable from the loyns of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, yet we know it is ſo, and where it is predominant in the ſight of God, and the more predominant that it is in any, the more loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſuch are in his ſight, and that in the very wombe.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:29921:21"/>
            <p>And this doth clear and fully reconcile the Mercy and Juſtice of God, and that againſt all the cavils and oppoſition whatſoever that can be objected; yea though never ſo many, either children or others, doe eternally periſh, and ſuffer the vengeance of eternall fire, for it is but wickedneſſe, <hi>ſpirituall wickedneſſe,</hi> that is veſſeld up <hi>againſt the day of wrath, and ſuffered with long patience, till it be fitted for deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> and that on purpoſe that <hi>he may ſhew his wrath, and hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne,</hi> and that <hi>he may make his power known</hi> how he can pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and that to all eternity, according to his Infinite Juſtice, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wrath and hatred of ſinne; as if need require, I ſhall ſhew at large, and anſwer all objections that can be produced, or that are held forth in your book or books, if this will not ſerve: but I love not to be tedious, if I may chuſe: And a word, they ſay, is ſufficient for wiſe men; I expect therefore that theſe brief hints may ſatisfie ſome, till I have opportunity and occaſion for a larger Treatiſe upon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, if it ſo pleaſeth God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:29921:22"/>
            <head>A brief Survey of the grand Abſurdities that neceſſarily follow their erroneous Doctrines and Tenets.</head>
            <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HEIR Doctrine implicitly denieth, that Faith is the gift of God, and that of free grace: And ſo they make faith as a thing in the power of the will of man, and ſo a thing meritorious in man, quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. <hi>For by grace we are ſaved through faith, and that not of our ſelves, it is the gift of God.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <hi>Not of works, leſt any man ſhould boast.</hi> And again, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>For we are his workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It utterly denieth the eternall omniſciency of God, and that <hi>his understanding is infinite, limiting the Holy One of Iſrael</hi> only to the fore-knowledge of a generall entire ſpecies of men, which he decreed to elect <hi>in the fulneſſe of time:</hi> As if his fore-knowledge, or counſell of his will before the world began, had not been capable nor comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, or at leaſt not extenſive, to foreſee the very particulars, and every occurrence that ſhould befall, from the beginning to the end, as he did the generals, and the ſpecies, &amp;c. quite contradictory to theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.5. <hi>Great is the Lord, and of great power, his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is infinite.</hi> Eph. 1.11. <hi>Being predeſtinate according to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of him who worketh all things according to the counſell of his own will.</hi> See allſo <hi>Acts</hi> 2.23. and 2.47. <hi>John</hi> 10.14. and <hi>verſ.</hi> 26, 27, 28, 29, 30.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They in theſe doctrines determine it to be an unjuſt thing in God to determine with himſelf before the world was, to <hi>make of the ſame lump</hi> of his own clay, <hi>one veſſel unto honour, and another unto diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour,</hi> one a <hi>veſſel of wrath, &amp;c.</hi> and another a <hi>veſſel of mercy,</hi> quite contradictory to the Apoſtles judgement, and to <hi>Davids</hi> allſo: <hi>What ſhall we ſay then? Is there unrighteouſneſſe with God? God forbid,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.14. though yet he did acknowledge, that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29921:22"/>God did even ſo, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24. And <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.17. <hi>The Lord is righteous in all his waies, and holy in all his works: Yea though it is not in him that willeth, nor in him that runneth, but in God that ſheweth mercy;</hi> and that <hi>he hath mercy on whom he will, and whom he will he hardeneth,</hi> (yea even <hi>he harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi>) as <hi>verſ.</hi> 17, 18. and 15.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It importeth, That God is as much engaged to ſhew mercy unto all, as to any at all; and ſo that God is unjuſt, if any be damned: As if there were no more cauſe nor reaſon in the ſight of God wherefore it is that he ſaveth ſuch, and the very ſame, who are his Elect, then if he ſhould ſave the Reprobates: denying in effect, that there was any cauſe why he <hi>loved Jacob, and hated Eſay,</hi> whiles <hi>they had not done either good or evill;</hi> as if the one had then been as good and lovely in the ſight of God, as was the other whom he had ſelected with his own hand from the very loyns of his naturall parents. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11, 12, 13.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It importeth, That ſome of Gods very Elect ſhall or may be damned; contrary to the Apoſtles judgement, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. from 28. to the end; where the Apoſtle concludes, That he <hi>was perſwaded, that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate ſuch,</hi> who are his Elect, <hi>from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. It importeth, That ſome <hi>of old ordained unto condemnation,</hi> and that <hi>are made</hi> (purpoſely) <hi>for the day of evill,</hi> as <hi>veſſels of wrath fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for destruction;</hi> yea that <hi>like brute beaſts are made to be taken and to be deſtroyed,</hi> may yet poſſibly be ſaved; as if the purpoſe of God could poſſibly be fruſtrate. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4, 5. <hi>Job</hi> 21.30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.15, 16, 17, 28, 19, &amp;c. and <hi>Jud.</hi> v. 4, 5.</p>
            <p n="7">7. This doctrine importeth, That none are Gods Elect but ſuch who come to years of diſcretion, and ſo to faith and repentance; though they would pretend the contrary; as if all children, dying in Infancy, ſhould certainly be ſaved: Whereas the conſequence of their doctrine concludes them all damned: For they plainly aſſert in their fift par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular wherein they diſſent from us,</p>
            <p>That <hi>the only decree of Election that can be aſſerted from the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, is for ſubſtance and effect, Whoſoever believeth ſhall be ſaved: As the only decree of Reprobation this, Whoſoever believeth not ſhall be damned.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:29921:23"/>
            <p n="8">8. It concludes it a thing neceſſary, for clearing the Mercy and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God, to make every particular perſon righteous, as <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency, before it can ſtand with Infinite Juſtice and Mercy to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him for ſin.</p>
            <p n="9">9. It concludeth in effect, That it could not ſtand with the Juſtice and Mercy of God to determine with himſelf before he created the Angels, to ſuffer ſome of them to fall, and after condemn them to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting torments for not keeping their firſt eſtate, as the Angels did; as is ſhewed in the book by neceſſary conſequence. See Reaſ. 6. to the ſecond particular.</p>
            <p n="10">10. This their doctrine holdeth forth, That both Men and Angels, yea and even all <hi>the whole creation, are nothing elſe but God himſelf:</hi> Which is an aſperſion blaſphemouſly impious; as you may ſee in the book, Reaſ. 6. to the ſecond particular.</p>
            <p n="11">11. This doctrine importeth, That no man can be aſſured that he ſhall not periſh eternally, till the end of his life; for they build all their aſſurance upon perſeverance in the faith, and that to the end: As though men could not know that they have allready <hi>eternall life abiding in</hi> them, which cannot poſſibly terminate or come to an end; being kept, not by their own power, but <hi>by the power of God, through faith unto ſalvation,</hi> as is at large proved in the book:</p>
            <p n="12">12. This doctrine teacheth expreſly, That it were more wiſedome in God, for making them more religious, and more obedient to his will, to hold them in ſuſpence all their life long, and give them no aſſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance:</p>
            <p>Whereas the Wiſedome and Mercy of God hath thought it better <hi>to give knowledge of ſalvation to his people, by the remſſion of their ſinnes; that they might ſerve him, without fear, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the daies of their life,</hi> Luke 1.74, 75, 77, 78, 79. See allſo Reaſ. 1. to the firſt particular.</p>
            <p n="13">13. This doctrine teacheth, That all children are alike holy or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy in the ſight of God by generation, and ſo till they come to years of diſcretion; and that not only Jewes <hi>by nature are the children of wrath as well as Gentiles, their father being an Amorite, and their mother an Hittite;</hi> and that <hi>all have ſinned,</hi> both Jewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and <hi>are</hi> therefore <hi>deprived of the glory of God,</hi> as ſo the text is clear.</p>
            <p>But all they ſay <hi>are in a like condition by generation,</hi> whatever pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29921:23"/>they are ſprung from, which quite contradicteth the Apoſtles aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, to wit, <hi>Elſe were your children unclean, but now are they holy,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. See all their fourth Reaſon of their diſſent from us, in their third particular.</p>
            <p n="14">14. It concludeth expreſly either manifeſt inconſiſtencies, or that the intent and purpoſe of God in his decree of Reprobation, is utterly fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and diſappointed:</p>
            <p>For particular ſixth they ſay, <hi>The intent, at leaſt the primary or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent intent of God in his decree of Reprobation, is the ſalvation, not the condemnation of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. It quite perverteth the phraſe of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the doctrines of the Goſpell:</p>
            <p>For they ſay, particular the fourth,</p>
            <p>That <hi>Faith and Repentance in particular perſons are not the fruits and effects of Election: But Election rather the fruit of theſe:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if Election decreed before the foundation of the world, could be the fruit of Faith and Repentance: And further, let any rationall man but read the order of the doctrine in theſe reſpects, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30. <hi>Whom he predeſtinated them he called, &amp;c.</hi> Not whom he called, them he after predeſtinated, for that were clear impropriety of language; for it were not predeſtination at all, if it were not a determination pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent unto calling, as here the Spirit of God renders it: And whether it be fitter to believe <hi>Paul</hi> or them, let themſelves judge.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
